[Music introduction]
Καλησπέρα, Αθήνα. Good afternoon, Athens.
Thank you for having me today.
You want disrupt? I got disrupt.
No. I have downright revolution.
We will talk about the most exciting, interesting,
and probably important technological innovation...
and invention in computer science
within the last twenty years.
I am here to talk about Bitcoin.
Perhaps you have heard about Bitcoin before.
Let's do a quick check. How many of
you have heard of bitcoin before today?
All right, we have a good crowd.
How many of you own bitcoin? Even better.
Bitcoin is digital money,
but it is so much more than that.
Bitcoin is digital money like the internet
is a fancy telephone, or all about email.
Money is just the first application.
Bitcoin is a technology, a currency,
and an international payment network.
It is decentralized. It doesn't rely on banks or
governments. We have never done this before...
in the history of humanity.
This invention is truly revolutionary. When we look
back, we will see that this was a historic moment...
in the evolution of not only computer science,
but a socio-political revolution in the making.
Let's get started. Bitcoin is digital money.
Euros and dollars are also digital, but
bitcoin is not owned by a government.
You can send it from anywhere in the world,
near instantaneously, securely, and for minimal fees.
Two days ago, we saw one of the largest transactions
ever recorded on the Bitcoin network.
Someone transferred $150 million [worth
of bitcoin] in [about ten minutes], for zero fees.
That should allow you to grasp how disruptive this
will be, in terms of international payment systems.
But this is just the beginning.
Bitcoin is a digital currency that was invented
in 2008 by a person called Satoshi Nakamoto.
He published a paper where he posited that he
had found a way to create a decentralized network,
that could achieve consensus / agreement
without any central controlling authority.
If you study computer science or distributed systems,
this is known as the Byzantine Generals' Problem.
It was first described in [1982].
Until 2008, it was an unsolved problem.
But we understood the importance of solving it.
Satoshi Nakamoto said that he had solved it.
Guess what happened next? Everybody laughed.
Many ignored and dismissed him.
He published the whitepaper. Three months later,
he published the software to start the Bitcoin network.
Bitcoin is not a company or organization.
It is a standard protocol, just like TCP/IP for the internet.
It is not owned by anyone [single entity].
It operates based on mathematical rules.
Everyone who participates in
the network must agree on them.
Bitcoin is a decentralized network of computers that,
through this consensus mechanism, agree on...
what transactions have occurred on the network,
and who currently owns what money.
If I send money to somebody else's "account"
in this peer-to-peer network, like sending email,
there is no one in the middle.
[The bitcoin transaction is broadcast] from
my computer to the recipient's computer,
without intervention.
Every ten minutes, the network agrees
on what transactions have happened,
without any centralized authority,
a kind of election that occurs electronically.
This particular solution [to the Byzantine Generals'
Problem] is far more important than currency.
Currency is just the first application that you
can build on a distributed consensus system.
Other applications include voting, stock ownership,
asset registration, notarization, and many others.
Applications we have never thought of before.
I discovered Bitcoin for the first time in 2011.
Since [the early days of] the internet,
I have not felt this feeling of being completely
overwhelmed by the possibilities I saw.
I was there at the dawn of the internet
in 1991, when it was pre-commercial.
I could see that this would change the world.
I told everyone around me, but no one believed me.
I have that exact same feeling about Bitcoin.
Some of you may have heard of bitcoin as a currency,
as a system of money that is currently
wildly high in price one day and low the next.
I am here to tell you to ignore the price, ignore bitcoin
the money, but understand Bitcoin the technology...
and the network it creates.
If we mess up the money,
we can just reboot another currency.
Bitcoin the technology cannot be uninvented.
It creates the possibility for decentralized organization...
on a scale never seen before on this planet.
Here is why it's important to me: today in the world,
approximately one billion people have banking,
access to credit and international finance capabilities,
primarily among the upper classes and western nations.
Six and a half billion people on this planet
have no connection to the world of [banking].
They operate in cash based societies with
very little access to any international resources.
But they don't need banks. Two billion people are already
on the internet; with a simple application download,
they can become participants in an international
economy, using an international currency that...
can be transmitted anywhere with [little
or] no fees, and no government controls.
They can connect to a world of international,
peer-to-peer finance. Bitcoin is the money of the people.
[It operates according to] mathematical rules
that everyone agrees on. No [centralized] control.
Bring six and a half billion people into productive society,
connecting them to the rest of the world,
is truly revolutionary.
First, we will start by affecting the payment processors,
these enormous companies that make it...
more expensive to send money
the poorer the destination country is.
This situation is exploitative and corrupt.
These organizations profit enormously for a function
that can be done in bitcoin for [little or no fee].
As an adage of the internet once went, I just replaced
your entire industry with a hundred lines of Python.
That is exactly what we will do with Bitcoin.
How can you use bitcoin today? Simply
speaking, bitcoin can operate as a currency.
You can think of it as buying a foreign currency.
You can connect to an exchange over the web,
wire some euros, and use them to buy bitcoin...
at the current exchange rate.
But that is not really the right way to do it.
We are entrepreneurs, right? We want to disrupt.
The best way [to obtain bitcoin] is by
finding a product or service you can offer...
that someone with bitcoin would want to buy.
Start by earning bitcoin.
If you want to start a business, there are
two barriers to becoming a global business.
The first barrier: it is difficult to transport
products and services across borders.
With the internet, we solved that. We can now create
products and services to sell that are virtual.
We could sell and deliver anywhere in the
world, but we still had one big problem.
How do we get paid?
Bitcoin solves that part.
It allows us to receive payments from
anywhere in the world, near instantaneously.
The Bitcoin network allows any individual to send
an amount as small one hundred millionth of a bitcoin,
which in today's terms is
a very tiny amount of money.
You can't do that with traditional
money and payment systems.
Credit cards were made in the 1950s,
certainly not made for an internet age.
Bitcoin is made for the internet age.
If you can send payments that are one hundredth
or thousandth of a euro, you can sell content...
with microtransactions.
You can collect tiny payments from millions of people
and then aggregate them to be worth something.
On the same network where you can send one
thousandth of a euro, you can send one billion euros.
The fee could be exactly the same, because
it depends on the size of the transaction in kilobytes,
not the [value of the money].
Let's look back at the internet, the lessons
we learned, and why bitcoin is important.
One of the most important principles
on the internet is neutrality.
The internet doesn't distinguish between
large organizations and small organizations.
It doesn't know the difference
between CNN and an Egyptian blogger.
It provides the opportunity for a blogger to speak to
the world with the same power of voice that CNN has.
Bitcoin is neutral to sender and recipient,
as well as to the value of a transaction.
That means every citizen and user of
Bitcoin has the ability to innovate in finance.
Instruments, payment systems, and currency,
with the same facilities that a bank has.
You can become Citibank.
That is truly revolutionary.
It [transforms] a hierarchical system of international
finance that achieved security by limiting access.
That is the method of "trust" on our payment systems.
You can't get in unless you are vetted.
Bitcoin turns that on its head, with a flat and
decentralized network where every node is equal.
The protocol is neutral to the transactions
and pushes innovation to the edge of the network.
This creates the same phenomenon we saw
on the internet: innovation without permission.
You don't need to ask anyone for your
application to be published on the internet.
You don't need to ask anyone to completely subvert
a new industry with your information technology.
On Bitcoin, you don't need to ask anyone to invent a
new financial instrument, payment system, or service.
You can just do it. You can just write the code.
You are now part of an international financial network.
You can run that code and come
in contact with millions of consumers.
Now, it is still early days. We don't yet have
the polished interfaces. It is difficult to use.
[The media says] it is used by criminals,
but it is not easy to see who is using bitcoin.
I have heard all of those [accusations] before.
When I was on the internet in 1991, it was "a den
of thieves," pornographers, pirates, and criminals.
But it didn't matter and it doesn't matter now,
because the same power of the technology,
used by a criminal to promote their criminal activities,
can be used by all the rest of us to do good,
to do incredible things all across the world.
There are more of us. Bitcoin creates an environment
that is ripe for innovation. It is not just a currency.
It is a technology, a network, and a currency.
I can tell you, I am very happy that bitcoin's price is
climbing. I own some bitcoins, and it feels kind of nice.
But I don't care about the price.
If Bitcoin crashed tomorrow morning,
the technology is still revolutionary.
If a website or application fails,
the internet doesn't go away.
If you understand that Bitcoin is a technology, not just
a currency, you can truly grasp its the importance.
Again, it is not just about us.
It is about the other six billion.
It is about bringing financial integration
that the world has never seen before.
From our perspective, it is a great technology
we can use for disruptive Innovation.
We can build some interesting services.
If you are a Kenyan farmer raising money to buy seeds,
you can join in decentralized, peer-to-peer lending,
and reach out to lenders all across the globe.
This is not just a technology, it is life-changing.
The impact Bitcoin will have on the vast majority of the
world which lives under repressive and corrupt regimes,
with central banks that impose
hyperinflation of 30% or more per month.
It is more important to see how
Bitcoin can affect all of those people.
There are two billion people on the internet;
only one billion of them have bank accounts.
We can change that. It will not be easy.
Make no mistake about it, when you
[introduce] a disruptive technology into...
the middle of the most powerful organizations
[and governments] on the planet, they won't like it.
Right now, we are still in the early stages.
To use a trite expression, "First they ignore us, then
they laugh at us, then they fight us, and then we win."
We are still at the laughing stage,
and that is quite all right.
By the time they start fighting us, they will have
already lost. This technology will be global.
More than $2.5 billion dollars has come from Chinese
investors who discovered a counterbalance...
to world domination by the global
reserve currency of the U.S. dollar.
There are about 180 currencies in the world,
but there is only one international currency.
There are about 180 currencies controlled by central
banks and governments, but only one is mathematical.
That is bitcoin. We will build more of them.
Cryptographic currencies will be
a mainstay of our financial future.
They will be part of the future of this planet.
They [can't be] uninvented, and it is as simple as that.
You cannot turn that omelet back into eggs.
There are already have more than
a hundred competing currencies.
This shows how quickly innovation has
exploded beyond bitcoin the currency.
There are many alternative coins, altcoins as
they're known, that use the same basic technology:
a decentralized consensus network and an asset ledger.
There [can be] other forms of currency that are
inflationary or deflationary, that use demurrage...
or negative interest rates.
Currencies that redistribute a proportion
of the income to charitable organisations.
We can invent new forms of
money and financial instruments.
Bitcoin is programmable money.
Once you have programmable money,
the possibilities are truly endless.
Many of the basic concepts in our current
system depend on legal contracts.
We can convert them into algorithmic contracts
that can be enforced on the Bitcoin network.
As I said before, there is no counterparty. If I choose to
send value to another part of the peer-to-peer network.
no one is in between.
if I invent a new form of money, I can deploy it
to the entire world and invite others to join me.
If you see that Bitcoin has the [potential]
to not only introduce money for the internet...
Because it is the perfect money for
the internet: instant, safe, and free.
Yes, it is money for the internet, but it is also
so much more. Bitcoin is the internet of money.
Currency is only the first application. If you grasp that,
you can look beyond the fad and the price volatility.
At its core, it is a revolutionary technology that will
change the world forever. Join me in this revolution.
Thank you. [Applause]